<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/contributorList.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<xml>
    <person>
        <persName>JOAN BERNOTT</persName>
        <birth when="unfindable"/>
        <death when="unfindable"/>
        <desc> American author of short science fiction whose work has appeared in the anthologies Again, Dangerous Visions and Cassandra Rising.</desc>
        <note source="quark">is a young writer who has also studied law and theater. This is her
            second appearance in QUARK/.</note>
    </person>
    <person>
        <persName>JOHN BRUNNER's</persName>
        <birth when="09-24-1934" where="Preston Crowmarsh"/>
        <death when="08-25-1995"/>
        <desc>British author of science fiction novels and stories.</desc>
        <note source="quark">most recent novels are The Jagged Orbit and Stand On Zanzibar, which
            won the Hugo Award as Best Science Fiction Novel of 1969.</note>
    </person>
    <person>
        <persName>ED BRYANT</persName>
        <birth when="08-27-1945" where="White Plains, New York"/>
        <death when="02-10-2017" where="Denver, Colorado"/>
       <desc> an American science fiction and horror writer sometimes associated with the Dangerous Visions series of anthologies that bolstered The New Wave.</desc>
        <note source="quark">has lived in <placeName>Wyoming</placeName>, Los Angeles, and New York. This is his second
            appearance in QUARK/.</note>
    </person>
    <person>
        <persName>IRA COHEN</persName>
        <birth when="02-03-1935" where="Bronx, New York"/>
        <death when="04-25-2011" where="New York"/>
        <desc>an American poet, publisher, photographer and filmmaker.</desc>
        <note source="quark">lives in New York. He has just completed his first film The Ivasion of
            the Thunderbolt Pagoda, in collaboration with Bill Vehr.</note>
    </person>
    <person>
        <persName>THOMAS M. DISCH</persName>
        <birth when="02-02-1940" where="Des Moines, Iowa"/>
        <death when="07-04-2008" where="Manhattan, NYC"/>
        <desc>was an American science fiction writer and poet.</desc>
        <note source="quark"> is the author of the novels The Genocides and Camp Concentration. He
            has also been widely published as a poet.</note>
    </person>
    <person><persName>SONYA DORMAN's</persName> 
        <birth when="06-04-1924" where="NYC"/>
        <death when="02-14-2005" where="Taos, New Mexico"/>
        <desc>Dorman published around two dozen science fiction short stories between 1961 and 1980, and she was associated with science fiction's "New Wave" of experimental writing.</desc>
        <note source="quark">fiction has appeared in
            Dangerous Visions and in Orbit; and her book, Poems, was pub- lished by Ohio University
            Press last fall.</note></person>
    <person>
        <persName>CAROL EMSHWILLER's</persName>
        <birth when="04-12-1921" where="Ann Arbor, Michigan"/>
        <death when="02-02-2019" where="Durham, North Carolina"/>
        <desc> was an American writer of avant garde short stories and science fiction who has won prizes ranging from the Nebula Award to the Philip K. Dick Award. Ursula K. Le Guin has called her "a major fabulist, a marvelous magical realist, one of the strongest, most complex, most consistently feminist voices in fiction". </desc>
        <note source="quark"> work is familiar to readers of Orbit and Dangerous Visions. She is
            presently com- pleting her first novel.</note>
    </person>
    <person>
        <persName>PHILIP JOSÉ FARMER</persName>
        <birth when="01-26-1918" where="North Terre Haute, Indiana"/>
        <death when="02-25-2009" where="Peoria, Illinois"/>
        <desc>an American author known for his science fiction and fantasy novels and short stories.</desc>
        <note source="quark">is the author of the novels Flesh, The Lovers, and Blown, and of the
            novella Riders of the Purple Wage, which appeared in Dangerous Visions, and won a Hugo
            Award.</note>
    </person>
    <person>
        <persName>RUSSELL FITZGERALD</persName>
        <birth when="12-29-1932" where="Bucks County, Pennsylvania"/>
        <death when="03-30-1978" />
        <note source="quark">is a painter and a writer, whose art work appeared in QUARK/1. He lives
            in Van- couver. NEMI FROST is a San Francisco painter.</note>
    </person>
    <person>
        <persName>MARILYN HACKER</persName>
        <birth when="11-27-1942"/>
        
        <desc>an American poet, translator and critic. She is Professor of English emerita at the City College of New York.</desc>
        <note source="quark">lives in San Francisco.</note>
    </person>
    <person>
        <persName>JAMES KIELTY</persName>
        <birth when="unfindable"/>
        <death when="unfindable"/>
        <note source="quark">is a linguist, a playwright, and a city planner. Several of his
            dramatic works have been pro- duced in San Francisco.</note>
    </person>
    <person>
        <persName>FRITZ LEIBER</persName>
        <birth when="12-24-1910" where="Chicago, Illinois"/>
        <death when="09-05-1992" where="San Francisco, California"/>
        <desc> an American writer of fantasy, horror, and science fiction. He was also a poet, actor in theater and films, playwright, and chess expert.</desc>
        <note source="quark">received both the Hugo Award and the Nebula Award of the Science
            Fiction Writers of Amer- ica for the story Gonna Roll Them Bones, which ap- peared in
            Dangerous Visions.</note>
    </person>
    <person>
        <persName>MAREK OBTULOWICZ</persName>
        <birth when="unfindable"/>
        <death when="unfindable"/>
        <note source="quark">is Polish, born in Cairo, and educated in England. At present, he lives
            in Milford, Pennsylvania, where he is working on a novel.</note>
    </person>
    <person>
        <persName>ALEXEI PANSHIN</persName>
        <birth when="1940-08-14" where="Lansing, Michigan"/>
        <death when="2022-08-21"/>
        <desc>an American writer and science fiction critic.</desc>
        <note source="quark"> is the author of the novels Masque World, The Thurb Revolution, and
            Rite Of Passage, which received the Nebula Award of the Science Fiction Writers of
            America.</note>
    </person>
    <person>
        <persName>ROGER PENNEY</persName>
        <birth when="1939"/>
        <desc>a singer, songwriter and multi-instrumentalist.</desc>
        <note source="quark">is a painter who lives in San Diego.</note>
    </person>
    <person>
        <persName>JAMES SALLIS</persName>
        <birth when="1944-12-21" where="Helena, Arkansas"/>
        <desc>an American crime writer who wrote a series of novels featuring the detective character Lew Griffin</desc>
        <note source="quark"> is a poet who lives in Milford, Pennsyl- vania. A collection of his
            short fiction, A Few Last Words, appeared last fall, and he is presently working on a
            book about American country music.</note>
    </person>
    <person>
        <persName>JOHN SLADEK</persName>
        <birth when="1937-12-15" where="Waverly, Iowa"/>
        <death when="2000-03-10" where="Minneapolis, Minnesota"/>
        <desc>was an American science fiction author</desc>
        <note source="quark">is the author of The Reproductive Sys- tem, published in this country
            as Mechasm; and co- author, with Thomas M. Disch, of Black Alice. He is living in
            England.</note>
    </person>
    <person>
        <persName>LELAND STONEY</persName>
        <birth when="unfindable"/>
        <death when="unfindable"/>
        <note source="quark">is a young poet living in San Fran- cisco.</note>
    </person>
    <person>
        <persName>LAURENCE YEP's</persName>
        <birth when="1948-06-14" where="San Francisco, California"/>
        <desc> an American writer</desc>
        <note source="quark">story, The Selchey Kids, appeared in World's Best Science Fiction. He
            is a student at the Uni- versity of California at Santa Cruz.</note>
    </person>
</xml>
