<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<xml>
    <person>
        <persName>JOAN BERNOTT</persName>
        <note source="quark">is a young writer who has also studied law and theater. This is her
            second appearance in QUARK/.</note>
    </person>
    <person>
        <persName>JOHN BRUNNER's</persName>
        <note source="quark">most recent novels are The Jagged Orbit and Stand On Zanzibar, which
            won the Hugo Award as Best Science Fiction Novel of 1969.</note>
    </person>
    <person>
        <persName>ED BRYANT</persName>
        <note source="quark">has lived in <placeName>Wyoming</placeName>, Los Angeles, and New York. This is his second
            appearance in QUARK/.</note>
    </person>
    <person>
        <persName>IRA COHEN</persName>
        <note source="quark">lives in New York. He has just completed his first film The Ivasion of
            the Thunderbolt Pagoda, in collaboration with Bill Vehr.</note>
    </person>
    <person>
        <persName>THOMAS M. DISCH</persName>
        <note source="quark"> is the author of the novels The Genocides and Camp Concentration. He
            has also been widely published as a poet.</note>
    </person>
    <person><persName>SONYA DORMAN's</persName> <note source="quark">fiction has appeared in
            Dangerous Visions and in Orbit; and her book, Poems, was pub- lished by Ohio University
            Press last fall.</note></person>
    <person>
        <persName>CAROL EMSHWILLER's</persName>
        <note source="quark"> work is familiar to readers of Orbit and Dangerous Visions. She is
            presently com- pleting her first novel.</note>
    </person>
    <person>
        <persName>PHILIP JOSÉ FARMER</persName>
        <note source="quark">is the author of the novels Flesh, The Lovers, and Blown, and of the
            novella Riders of the Purple Wage, which appeared in Dangerous Visions, and won a Hugo
            Award.</note>
    </person>
    <person>
        <persName>RUSSELL FITZGERALD</persName>
        <note source="quark">is a painter and a writer, whose art work appeared in QUARK/1. He lives
            in Van- couver. NEMI FROST is a San Francisco painter.</note>
    </person>
    <person>
        <persName>MARILYN HACKER</persName>
        <note source="quark">lives in San Francisco.</note>
    </person>
    <person>
        <persName>JAMES KIELTY</persName>
        <note source="quark">is a linguist, a playwright, and a city planner. Several of his
            dramatic works have been pro- duced in San Francisco.</note>
    </person>
    <person>
        <persName>FRITZ LEIBER</persName>
        <note source="quark">received both the Hugo Award and the Nebula Award of the Science
            Fiction Writers of Amer- ica for the story Gonna Roll Them Bones, which ap- peared in
            Dangerous Visions.</note>
    </person>
    <person>
        <persName>MAREK OBTULOWICZ</persName>
        <note source="quark">is Polish, born in Cairo, and educated in England. At present, he lives
            in Milford, Pennsylvania, where he is working on a novel.</note>
    </person>
    <person>
        <persName>ALEXEI PANSHIN</persName>
        <note source="quark"> is the author of the novels Masque World, The Thurb Revolution, and
            Rite Of Passage, which received the Nebula Award of the Science Fiction Writers of
            America.</note>
    </person>
    <person>
        <persName>ROGER PENNEY</persName>
        <note source="quark">is a painter who lives in San Diego.</note>
    </person>
    <person>
        <persName>JAMES SALLIS</persName>
        <note source="quark"> is a poet who lives in Milford, Pennsyl- vania. A collection of his
            short fiction, A Few Last Words, appeared last fall, and he is presently working on a
            book about American country music.</note>
    </person>
    <person>
        <persName>JOHN SLADEK</persName>
        <note source="quark">is the author of The Reproductive Sys- tem, published in this country
            as Mechasm; and co- author, with Thomas M. Disch, of Black Alice. He is living in
            England.</note>
    </person>
    <person>
        <persName>LELAND STONEY</persName>
        <note source="quark">is a young poet living in San Fran- cisco.</note>
    </person>
    <person>
        <persName>LAURENCE YEP's</persName>
        <note source="quark">story, The Selchey Kids, appeared in World's Best Science Fiction. He
            is a student at the Uni- versity of California at Santa Cruz.</note>
    </person>
</xml>
