<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/contributorList.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<xml>
    
    <title>CONTRIBUTORS' NOTES</title>
    
    
  <listPerson type="contributor">  
      
   <person xml:id="Adam_Helen"><persName>HELEN ADAM</persName>
       <!-- more info you provide like birth / death dates?-->
       <birth when=""/>
       <death when=""/>
       <note source="Quark">is a Scots-born poet, who now lives in
    New York City. She is the co-author of the play San
    Francisco's Burning, which has been presented in San
    Francisco and in New York.</note>
   </person>
   <person> HILARY BAILEY's most recent American publication
    was the novella The Fall of Frenchy Steiner. She lives in
    London, with her husband, Michael Moorcock.
    GREG BENFORD's first novel, Deeper than the Darkness, is an expansion of his novelette of the same title,
    which was nominated for the Nebula Award of the
    Science Fiction Writers of America.</person>
    <person>JOAN BERNOTT attended the Clarion College Science
    Fiction Writers' Workshop.</person>
    <person>SANDRA BOUCHER is a young writer who lives in San
    Francisco.</person>
    ED BRYANT has a Master's degree in English from the
    University of Wyoming. He lives in Los Angeles.
    SAMUEL R. DELANY lives currently in San Francisco.
    THOMAS M. DISCH, author of Camp Concentration,
    The Genocides, and Echo Round His Bones, lives in New
    York.
    GARDNER R. DOZOIS recently returned to the United
    States after spending four years abroad. He now lives in
    New York City.
    238 
    GORDON EKLUND lives with his wife and child in San
    Francisco.
    RUSSELL FITZGERALD is a painter, designer, and
    writer. He lives in New York with his wife and twin
    daughters.
    STEPHEN GILDEN is a painter and cartoonist who has
    lived in Texas, New York, and, currently, California.
    H. B. HICKEY lives in Los Angeles.
    R. A. LAFFERTY is the author of Space Chantey, The
    Reefs of Earth, Past Master, and, most recently, Fourth
    Mansions.
    URSULA K. LEGUIN received the Nebula Award of the
    Science Fiction Writers of America for her novel The
    Left Hand of Darkness.
    LINK is a young poet who lives in San Francisco. He
    edited the literary magazine Cow.
    CHRISTOPHER PRIEST is a young English writer.
    JOANNA RUSS is the author of And Chaos Died and
    Picnic on Paradise. She teaches creative writing at Cornell
    University.
    GEORGE STANLEY's collection of poems, You, will
    appear this winter from Grove Press, and will include
    Orion.
    A. E. VAN VOGT is the author of The Silkie, The
    Weapon Shops of lsher, and Sian. 
  
  </listPerson>
    
    <listPerson>
        <!-- We can use XSLT to pull the names of all the people the project team tags, and then populate another list that either lives in 
        this file or elsewhere-->
    </listPerson>
    
</xml>
