<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- 
     pb = pageBottom 
     PoI = Point of Interest
     abbr = Abbreviated
-->


<xml>
    <title type="essay">CRITICAL METHODS: SPECULATIVE FICTION</title>
    <p> The historical discussion of the development of some area of art, while often illuminating,
        does not necessarily exhaust that area. The development of a particular literary technique
        or theme over several decades through several writers, often in several countries, is not
        completely solved by a chronological listing of who did what first.</p>
    <p paragraph="PoI"> The historical literary critic tends to see literary progress as a process
        rather like this: some seminal genius invents · a form; another refines it; still a third
        brings it to heretofore unimagined perfection; while a later fourth now takes the form into
        decadence; finally a new genius appears who, reacting against this decadence, invents a new
        form, and the cycle begins again.</p>
    <!-- Paragraph describes a way of viewing literary progress -->
    <p> But this view only traces a single thread through what is essentially a tapestry of
        aesthetic productions. The line, by definition, tries to connect the high points. Frequently
        enough, these high points are, in reality, connected. But just as frequently they are
        connected more strongly to other works and situations totally off this line. Historical
        artistic progress only exists by virtue of the perspective lent by hindsight.</p>
    <p> Of the many ways in which an artist can be influenced by other art, the historical
        art~critic over-concentrates on two: the desire to imitate excellence, which, in genius,
        sometimes results in former excellence surpassed; and the distaste for the mediocre, the
        stultified, the inflexible, which, again in genius, can result in new forms.</p>
    <p paragraph="split"> But there are other ways to be influenced. One artist may find a work that
        seems to him to have an interesting kernel, but strikes him as so badly executed that he
        feels he can treat the same substance far more rewardingly. More frequently, I suspect, he
        finds an interesting technique employed to decorate a vapid hollow center, and <pb n="182"/>
        uses it to ornament his own central concerns. It is still a little odd to look at whom some
        major authors felt to be their greatest influences. Thus <persName>Coleridge</persName> says
        that the sonnets of the country <persName>Reverend William Lisle Bowles</persName>, insipid
        and artificial by today's standards, were the literary <word type="marked"
        >epiphany</word><!-- a manifestation of a divine or supernatural being. --> of his youth.
        And Keats was practically fixated on the eighteenth-century boy-poet <persName>Thomas
            Chatterton</persName>, who, after perpetrating a series of forgeries of <word type="term">Middle English</word>
        poems, allegedly the work of a nonexistent monk, <persName>Thomas Rowley</persName>, came to
            <location>London</location> and within the year committed suicide by taking rat poison,
        aged seventeen years and nine months.</p>
    <p>Let us look at the development of one of the narrative techniques that practically alone
        supports science fiction: expertise-that method by which an author, deploying a handful of
        esoteric facts, creates the impression that he, or more often a character in his story, is
        an expert in some given field. It was formulated as an outgrowth of <word type="term">French
            Naturalism</word><!--  Literary naturalism emphasizes observation and the scientific method in the fictional portrayal of reality. Naturalism includes detachment, in which the author maintains an impersonal tone and disinterested point of view; -->
        by a writer who began as a younger disciple of
        <persName>Zola</persName><!-- Well known writer and influence on French Naturalism -->,
            <persName>Joris Karl Huysmans</persName>. He brought the technique to pitch in his
        extremely influential novel <title type="book">A Rebours</title>, <Publication type="date">published in <year when="1884">1884</year>, a year after</Publication> <title type="book">Treasure
            Island</title>, a year before <title type="book">She</title>. But where the
            <groupName>Naturalists</groupName> employed exhaustive research to give density to their
        endless chronicles of common people at common professions, <persName>Huysmans</persName> used comparatively
        superficial research to give an impression of thorough familiarity with a whole series of
        bizarre and exotic subjects, including late <word type="term">Latin literature</word>, <word type="term">horticulture</word>, and <word type="book">perfumery</word>,
        to list only a few.</p>
    <p> Till its recent reissue, I doubt if many currently working SF writers had read <persName>Huysman's</persName>
        plotless, characterless, yet totally enthralling novel. But you can find the technique
        employed in exactly the same manner in something as recent as <persName>Thomas Disch's</persName> <title type="book">Camp
        Concentration</title>. Still, though I cannot prove it, I am sure there is a line (more likely a
        web) of writers who read writers who read <persName>Huysmans</persName>, and who took from one another this
        obviously effective technique, as directly as <persName>Wilde</persName> took the cadences
        and repetitions in the dialogue for <title type="opera">Salome</title> from <persName>Poe's</persName> Politian.</p>
    <pb n="183"/>
    <p>Indeed, we know <persName>Huysmans</persName> was familiar with <persName>Poe</persName>. <persName>Poe</persName> and <persName>Baudelaire</persName> are the most frequently
        mentioned authors in <title type="book">A Rebours</title>. <persName>Huysmans</persName> undoubtedly knew <persName>Poe</persName> through the superb <persName>Baudelaire</persName>
        translations, which, from their impact on French literature, quite possibly have more merit
        than the originals. In <title type="book">A Rebours</title>, <title type="book">The N arrative of A. Gordon Pym</title> is mentioned by name, a
        work which· <persName>Poe</persName> dots with much nautical expertise to make his sailor narrator convincing, on
        a thoroughly unreal voyage to the <location>South Pole</location>, that ends with the appearance of the <persName type="character">White
        Goddess</persName> herself. This, and the similar use of expertise in the tales of ratiocination, could
        easily have prompted <persName>Huysmans</persName> to make the jump between using expertise to validate the
        commonplace to evoking the exotic and bizarre. (For those of you interested who are unable
        to acquire the book, you can get some idea of the flavor of <title type="book">A Rebours</title> from Chapter Eight of
        <persName>Oscar Wilde's</persName> <title type="book">Picture of Dorian Grey</title>, which is a pastiche of <persName>Huysmans</persName>; the mysterious
        yellow-backed French novel after which <persName>Dorian</persName> patterns his life was immediately identified
        by the Victorian public as <title type="book">A Rebours</title>, which was confirmed by <persName>Wilde</persName> during the <name type="event">Queensbury
        trial</name>;. the book had achieved a reputation for decadence and corruption, as sexual oddities
        were another subject that <persName>Huysmans</persName> explored with his newly perfected technique.)</p>
    <p> One place where the connection is clearly drawn is in <persName>Alfred Bester's</persName> early horror novella,
        <title type="novella">Astarte Was a Lady</title>. The opening of the novella is practically a rewrite of the opening
        movements of <title type="book">A Rebours</title>. The relation is so close that I am fairly sure that <persName>Bester</persName>, an
        erudite author who studs his work with overt .and covert literary references, was
        undoubtedly familiar with it when Astarte was published in the late thirties in <title>Unknown</title>.</p>
    <p>And <persName>Bester</persName> is easily the <abbr>SF</abbr> writer who brought expertise to its full fruition in his
        work.</p>
    <p paragraph="split">Thus an <abbr>SF</abbr> literary technique has its burgeonings in an <word type="term">American fantasist</word>,
        passes over the ocean to be translated by a great poet, is furthered by a French <altLang language="French">fin de
        siecle decadent</altLang>, and returns a hundred years later to American magazine fiction. In the
        early sixties, it moved</p>
    <pb n="184"/>
    <p>away to support the <abbr>pseudo-SF</abbr> James-Bond-style thriller, which would thoroughly collapse
        without it. But this is the way the web of influence works, passing in and out of the genre,
        crossing national and language boundaries, and returning, completely frustrating the
        historical critic who would keep everything in its proper path.</p>
    <p> In the same way, the didactic methods of <persName>Robert Heinlein</persName> owe a great deal to <persName>Shaw's</persName> comedies
        of ideas, far more than to <persName>Wells</persName> and <persName>Verne</persName>. Indeed, part of that mystical optimism that
        pervades so much of <abbr>SF</abbr> is a product of a process that we can see in the ending of <persName>Shaw's</persName><title type="drama"> Man
        and Superman</title>, <persName>Twain's</persName> <title type="novel">Mysterious Stranger</title>, <persName>Kipling's</persName> <title type="book">Children of the Zodiac</title>, and <persName>Poe's</persName><title type="book">
        Eukera</title>, a process shared by such <abbr>SF</abbr> classics as <persName>Heinlein's</persName> <title type="novel">Stranger in a Strange Land</title>,
        <persName>Clarke's</persName> <title type="novel">Childhood End</title>, <title type="novel">Sturgeon's More Than Human</title>, and <persName>Disch's</persName> <title type="novel">Camp Concentration</title>: any
        attempt to be totally rational about such a basically mystical subject as man's ultimate
        place in the universe tends to squeeze all the mysticism into one bright chunk that blurs
        all resolutions at the end.</p>
    <p paragraph="split"> Contrary to what might be expected, it is much harder to trace the
        development of a strictly limited subject than of a general one. To take an absurd example:
        it would be fairly intriguing to discuss the growth of interest in late medieval, Gallic
        song-forms among poets of. the past hundred years. From Joyce's villanelle in Portrait of
        the Artist to Pound's and Auden's experiments with the sestina and canzone, or in the
        turn-of-the-century profusion of rondels and rondolets, there is great give and take among
        the general run of poets, with a few enduring examples that give significance to the whole
        discussion. It would be quite another matter to discuss the use of only one medieval song
        form, let us say the triolet, over the same period. One could cite, in a historical list,
        Rimbaud's "Le Coeur vole," go on to mention Ernest Dowson's and Lionel Johnson's attempts,
        (contemporaries of Yeats) and perhaps Sara Teasdale's "Why Do You Walk Through the Fields in
        Gloves" from the twenties. For what little it's worth, I would hazard a guess that Dowson
        had read Rimbaud and that Teasdale had read Dow-<pb n="185">185</pb> son. But this gives us
        only a list, not a development. The fact is, the impulse to write one's first triolet is
        simply to see if one can do it. But once the form is learned, the impulse for the second or
        third might just as easily come from reading Gray's Anatomy as reading Milton, from the
        ubiquitous unhappy love affair, or the poached egg you had for breakfast.</p>
    <p> To explore the development of SF poses a similar problem. Though its audience is growing, it
        is still a limited form, a specialized genre. The historical approach has been tried many
        times. But the fact is, if SF had been influenced only by itself, it would have strangled
        long since. If it did not continually influence areas outside itself, we would not have the
        present increase of interest. Simply because it is limited,- a simple listing of which
        writer wrote what first will not do, whether one starts with Wells or Lucian.</p>
    <p> The usual historical approach, at present, is the common intellectual property of
        practically anyone who knows that SF stands for science fiction. It begins with Wells and
        Verne and more or less ends with Heinlein and Bradbury. Anyone whose interest extends to
        actually reading it knows that an editor named Campbell caused some major changes, and
        before that an editor named Hugo Gernsback was· important.</p>
    <p> My own feeling is that, in an attempt to give respectability to American SF, much too much
        has been made of the relation between English Victorian, or Wellsian SF, and post-Gernsback,
        or Modern. Risking the other extreme, I propose that the relation actually is no stronger
        (or weaker) than the passage of the idea that it was possible to write stories and novels
        set in the future. Let me make some sweeping statements about areas that have been covered
        much more thoroughly by a host of other writers. Wells' "Romances of the Future" come from
        much the same impulse that produced his monumental multivolume An Outline of History. The
        future stories were an outgrowth of the perfectly viable fancy that history might well
        continue beyond the present. Both the historical work and the SF, however, fell out of <pb
            n="186"/> the same twin Victorian views: that man's knowledge., in general, and his
        technology, in particular, develop in a more or less orderly way; and also that, in a given
        situation, human behavior will always be more or less the same, no matter when, or
        where.</p>
    <p paragraph="split">Both of these views, however, are Victorian prejudices. Technology has
        always run in both constructive and destructive directions at once. While Rome's engineers
        built amazing stone aqueducts with engineering techniques that astound us today, her
        aristocracy was unintentionally committing mass suicide with lead-based cosmetics and
        lead-lined wine-jars. Pasteur invented vaccination, which prevented smallpox, and which,
        when the technique was finally extended to typhoid, typhus, diphtheria, and yellow fever,
        made possible the Second World War-till then, it would have been unthinkable to mass so many
        soldiers in such unsanitary conditions without having them completely wiped out by
        communicable diseases. Yet, from modern military medicine come the new discoveries in
        bioelectronics, and the science which Pasteur invented to preserve life is ultimately rushed
        on a step. Man's technical achievements, like his aesthetic ones, do not form a single line,
        but a web, in which numerous .lines can be traced. Indeed, they sit in the same web. Any new
        discovery, from Oveonic devices to the revelation of a new ecological relationship, may
        spark changes in all directions, with good and bad results, that will cycle and echo,
        perhaps for centuries, in science, economics, and art, Nor is human behavior any more stable
        from age to age, place to place. In seventeenth-century India, a Buddhist priest went to sit
        at the gate of a Sultan who had treated his people too harshly. At the gate, the priest
        refused to eat or drink, and inside the house, the Sultan died from guilt and shame; while,
        in eighteenth-century France, the Queen, upon being told that the people had no bread,
        responds with the line that has become an emblem of political irresponsibility, "Then let
        them eat cake." In Greece in the ninth century B.C., the accidental revelation of incest
        between mother and son resulted <pb n="187"/> in suicide and self-mutilation; five hundred
        years later in Persia, parents and children who could prove that they had indulged in carnal
        relations were elevated to the rank of holy men and women with great honor and reverence. A
        Mediterranean, upon discovering his wife in the arms of another man, commits a brutal double
        murder, while an Eskimo, receiving a stranger into his igloo, graciously offers his wife for
        sexual pleasure during the length of the visitor's stay. (And the unbiased student of
        anthropology could further cite societies or times' in which incest was neither holy nor
        anathematic, but commonplace, or in which the disposal of her own, and possibly her
        spouse's, sexual favors was the woman's prerogative.) In nineteenth-century Russia, certain
        aristocrats organized weekend hunts for their guests, with dogs, horses, and rifles. The
        quarry, slaughtered and hung up for show in the barn, was thirteen- and fourteen-year-old
        peasant boys. Today, in Vietnam, seventeen- and eighteen-year-old American boys amuse
        themselves shooting at war prisoners through the stockade fence, while, in the states from
        which these boys hail, the death penalty is finally declared illegal as a primitive and
        barbaric custom.</p>
    <p>There is nothing universal about the laws of human nature, at least as the Victorians
        pictured them. My readers sensitive to cultural resonances will probably sense them from all
        these examples of behavior as they look around our own culture. But that is because the
        human mind resonates. To try and construct historical chains of causation between these
        types of behavior and our own society is to miss the point. The human animal is potentially
        capable of any behavior. The feeling of resonance is a personal response to that
        potential.</p>
    <p>Not only can the human animal behave in any way, the human psyche can approve or disapprove
        of any behavior. Thus, in one cultural enclave, the supreme moral act is the eating of bread
        and the drinking of wine; in another it is the act of sexual congress itself; while in
        another it is the disemboweling of babies. One group feels that avarice and selfishness are
        the roots of all evil. Another feels that uneducated altruism is the source of all <pb
            n="188"/> the world's mismanagement, and that altruistic acts are the basic sins that
        rot the society. One group feels that ignorance is the cause of all the world's trouble.
        Another feels that all knowledge leads to pain. </p>
    <p> No, the Victorian supposition of the linear moral logic of human progress and the inflexible
        catholicity of human nature have been left rather far behind. But these ideas are as
        inchoate in Wells's SF as they are in his history.</p>
    <p> To look at Gernsback-or rather, Gernsback and his progeny-in relation to Wells, questions of
        literary merit set momentarily aside, immense differences appear immediately.</p>
    <p> Gernsback was 'interested solely in the wonderful things progress might bring. As a popular
        entertainer, he was just as interested in the possible as he was in the probable. In his own
        novel, Ralph 124C41+, there is the chaste ghost of a love interest, but it vanishes amidst a
        host of marvelous gadgets. His use of behavior went only so far as it showed what things
        could do. Most of the objects were socially beneficial. When they were not, they were in the
        hands of the criminals that Ralph truimphed over. But there was none of the socially
        functional logic in which Wells indulged: Since this is scientifically infeasible, it would
        not be socially beneficial to discuss what might come out of it. The logic behind
        Ge.rnsback's view of SF, which persists today, is rather: Even though current technology
        claims this is impossible, if we were to achieve it, look at what marvels might result.</p>
    <p> It is just this basic concern with thingness that makes me insist that the initial impulse
        behind SF, despite the primitive and vulgar verbal trappings, was closer to the impulse
        behind poetry than it was to the impulse behind ordinary narrative fiction.</p>
    <p paragraph="split"> As another critic has said, in another context, "Poetry is concerned with
        the thingness of things." The new American SF took on the practically incantatory task of
        naming nonexistent objects, then investing them with reality by a host of methods,
        technological and pseudotechnological explanations, imbedding them in dramatic situations,
        or just inculcating them by pure repetition: <pb n="189"/>
        <list type="item">
            <Lo>Television</Lo>
            <Lo>Rocketship</Lo>
            <Lo>Waldo</Lo>
            <Lo>Spacesuit</Lo>
        </list> But this is SF at its most primitive. The incantatory function-a better word than
        "predictive" -is no more the chief concern of modern SF than it is the concern of modern
        poetry; though remnants of it still linger in everything from Cordwainer Smith's
        "ornithopters" to Greg Benford's "brain tapping." Here is the place to note, I think, that
        when the British SF magazine New Worlds was awarded a London Arts Council subsidy, one of
        the testimonials, from a member of the editorial board of the Oxford Unabridged Dictionary
        of the English Language, explained that science fiction was the most fertile area of writing
        in the production of new words which endured in the language-a position held up till the
        mid-thirties by poetry.</p>
    <p>Because it was unconcerned with behavior at its beginnings, SF was eventually able to reflect
        the breakdown of Victorian behavioral concepts which, for all his advanced thinking, had
        strictured Wells. It has been remarked, everywhere that man has noted in detail what goes on
        around him, (you will find the idea in Confucious and in Plato) that the objects around him
        do influence his behavior, as well as how he judges the behavior of himself and others. The
        philosophers of aesthetics never tire of reminding us that the man who grows up in a
        beautiful and aesthetically interesting environment behaves very differently from the man
        raised among ugly, squalid surroundings. The Victorian progressives added to this, that a
        person raised in an efficient, healthy, leisurely environment behaves quite differently from
        one raised amidst harrying inefficiency and disease. The aesthete quickly points out that
        the behavior of the person brought up with efficiency is still not the same as that of the
        person brought up with beauty.</p>
    <p> McLuhan formulates this more precisely when he explains that any man-made object, and a good
        many natural ones, as they express or reflect aspects of man's <pb n="190"/> inner
        consciousness, become factors in the equations governing communication as soon as they come
        into our perception.</p>
    <p>But well before McLuhan had put this so succinctlyindeed, SF was to prompt McLuhan to this
        statement, another example of influence across boundaries-American SF writers, freed from
        the strictures of the probable, left to soar in the byways of the possible, not bound by the
        concept of universal human nature, in a country that was itself a potpourri of different
        cultural behavior patterns, sat contemplating marvelous objects in the theater of the mind.
        Slowly, intuitions of the way in which these objects might affect behavior began to appear
        in the stories. Editor Campbell was astute enough to see that this was perhaps the most
        powerful tool in the realization of these marvelous inventions. He encouraged his writers to
        use this tool, to make the focus of the stories the juncture between the object and the
        behavior it causes. As the writers followed Campbell, SF began to grow up.</p>
    <p> By much the same process that poetry expanded beyond its beginnings in ritualistic chant and
        incantation, to become a way to paint· all that is human, and etch much that is divine, so
        SF became able to reflect, focus, and diffract the relations between man and his universe,
        as it included other men, as it included all that man could create, all he could
        conceive.</p>
    <p> Already, how much more potentially complex a template we have than the one left us by
        Victorian Utopian fiction. The Utopian fictions of Butler, Bellamy, Wells, as well as the
        later Huxley and Orwell, exhaust themselves by taking sides in the terribly limiting
        argument: "Regard this new society. You say it's good, but I say it's bad." Or, "You say
        it's bad, but I say it's good."</p>
    <p> Auden has pointed out in his collection of essays, The Dyer's Hand, and then gone on to
        examine in his cycle of poems, Horae Canonicae, that this argument is essentially a split in
        temperaments, not a logical division at all.</p>
    <p> There are, and always will be, those people who see hope in progress. Au den calls their
        perfect world New Jerusalem. In New Jerusalem, hunger and disease have <pb n="191"/> been
        abolished through science, man is free of drudgery and pain, and from it he can explore any
        aspect of the physical world in any way he wishes, assured that he has the power to best it
        should nature demand a contest. There are, and always will be, people who wish, in Auden's
        words, to return to Eden. He calls their perfect world Arcadia. In Arcadia, food is grown by
        individual farmers, and technology never progresses beyond what one man can make with his
        own hands. Man is at one with nature, who strengthens him for his explorations of the inner
        life; thus all that he creates will be in natural good taste; and good will and camaraderie
        govern his relation with his fellows.</p>
    <p> To the man who yearns after Arcadia, any movement to establish New Jerusalem will always
        look like a step toward Brave New World, that mechanized, dehumanized, and standardized
        environment, where the gaudy and meretricious alternates with the insufferably dull; where,
        if physical hardship is reduced, it is at the price of the most humiliating spiritual
        brutalization.</p>
    <p> In the same way, the man who dreams of New Jerusalem sees any serious attempt to establish
        an Arcadia as a retreat to the Land of Flies: that place of provincial ignorance, fear,
        disease, and dirt, where man is prey to the untrammeled demons of his own superstition, as
        well as any caprice of nature: fire, flood, storm, or earthquake.</p>
    <p> The final argument for either of these views must ultimately be expressed: in the
        environment I prefer, I would find it easier to treat the variety of my fellows with
        affection, tolerance, and respect. And this, as Auden says, is a statement of personal
        preference, not a logical social dictum. With the variety of fellow beings what it is, the
        argument will probably always be here.</p>
    <p> Modern SF has gone beyond this irreconcilable Utopian/Dystopian conflict to produce a more
        fruitful model against which to compare human development.</p>
    <p> The SF writers working under Campbell, and even more so with Horace Gold, began to cluster
        their new and wonderful objects into the same story, or novel. And whole new systems and
        syndromes of behavior began <pb n="192"/> to emerge. Damon Knight, in In Search of Wonder,
        notes Charles Harness's The Paradox Man as the first really successful "reduplicated" novel
        where an ordered sarabande of wonders reflect and complement each other till they have
        produced a completely new world, in which the technological relation to ours is minimal. Now
        the writers began to explore these infinitely multiplicated worlds, filled with wondrous
        things, where the roads and the paintings moved, where religion took the place of
        government, and advertising took the place of religion, where travel could be instantaneous
        between anywhere and anywhere else, where the sky was metal, and women wore live goldfish in
        the transparent heels of their shoes. Within these worlds, the impossible relieves the
        probable, and the possible illuminates the improbable. And the author's aim is neither to
        condemn nor to condone, but to explore both the worlds and their behaviors for the sake of
        the exploration, again an aim far closer to poetry than to any sociological brand of
        fiction. </p>
    <p> As soon as the Wellsian parameters are put aside, far more protean ones emerge from modern
        SF almost at once.</p>
    <p> In the most truly Utopian of New Jerusalems, sometime you will find yourself in front of an
        innocuous-looking door; go through it, and you will find yourself, aghast, before some
        remnant of the Land of the Flies; in the most dehumanized Brave New World, one evening as
        you wander through the dreary public park, sunset bronzing fallen leaves will momentarily
        usher you into the most marvelous autumn evening in Arcadia. Similarly, in either Arcadia or
        the Land of the Flies, plans can be begun for either Brave New World or New Jerusalem.</p>
    <p> SF has been called a romantic and affirmative literature. J. G. Ballard has gone so far as
        to point out, quite justly, that the bulk of it is rendered trivial by its nai:vely
        boundless optimism. But we do not judge the novel by the plethora of sloppy romances or
        boneheaded adventures that make up the statistically vast majority of examples; if we did,
        it might lead us to say the same of all areas of literature, novel, poetry, or drama; with
        no selection by <pb n="193"/> merit, I'm afraid on a statistical listing, expressions of the
        vapidly happy would far outnumber expressions of the tragic on whatever level. As any other
        area of art is judged by its finest examples, and not ·by the oceans of mediocrity that
        these high points rise above, this is the way SF must be judged. There are threads of
        tragedy running through the works of Sturgeon and Bester (they can even be unraveled from
        Heinlein), not to mention Disch, Zelazny, and Russ, as well as Ballard's own tales of ruined
        worlds, decadent resortists, and the more recent fragmented visions of stasis and violence.
        And one would be hard-pressed to call the comic vision of Vonnegut, Sladek, and Lafferty
        "naively optimistic". </p>
    <p> If SF is affirmative, it is not through any obligatory happy ending, but rather through the
        breadth of vision it affords through the complexed interweave of these multiple visions of
        man's origins and his destinations. Certainly such breadth of vision does not abolish
        tragedy. But it does make a little rarer the particular needless tragedy that comes from a
        certain type of narrow-mindedness.</p>
    <p> Academic SF criticism, fixed in the historical approach, wastes a great deal of time trying
        to approach modern SF works in Utopian/Dystopian terms-works whose value is precisely in
        that they are a reaction to such onesided thinking. It is much more fruitful if modern works
        are examined in terms of what they contain of all these mythic views of the world. (Carl
        Becker has suggested that New Jerusalem and Brave New World are the only two new myths that
        the twentieth century has produced.) </p>
    <p> It is absurd to argue whether Asimov's Foundation trilogy represents a Utopian or a
        Dystopian view of society; its theme is the way in which a series of interrelated societies,
        over a historical period, force each other at different times back and forth from Utopian to
        Dystopian phases.</p>
    <p>
        <altFont type="bold"> In The Stars My Destination, the Jaunt Re-education program is clearly
            a product of New Jerusalem. Equally clearly, the Presteign Clan, with its four hundred
            ninetyseven surgically identical Mr. Prestos, is from Brave New World. And they exist
            side by side in the same work.</altFont>
    </p>
    <pb n="194"/>

    <p>Gully, though he has been uniformed by Brave New World, begins as · an unformed lump of
        elemental violence, ignorance, and endurance from the Land of the Flies. Robin Wednesbury's
        home in the re-established forests of Greenbay, insulated from its neighbors, with her
        collection of books and records, exists in Arcadia. Gully I Cali ban implodes into it with
        violence and rape; and Robin and Arcadia survive to both help and hinder him as the novel
        goes on. This sort of optimism, emblematically as it is handled, is far more true to life
        than the Victorian convention that equates "dishonor" with death -though in black Robin's
        eventual marriage to the only other non-Caucasian in the book, the Oriental YangY' eovil,
        there is a hint of acceptance of an equally nasty American convention.</p>
    <p>Because all four visions are offered in the best modern SF, no single one is allowed to
        paralyze us with terror or lull us into muddle-headed euphoria. </p>
    <p>What I would like to see in serious SF criticism, among other things, is an examination of
        how all four of these mythic visions sit in concert in given works. And I would like to see
        an end to the lauding (or dismissal) of works because they do (or do not) reflect only one. </p>
    <p name="">-Samuel R. Delany </p>
    <blankSpace> </blankSpace>
    <pb n="195"/>
</xml>
