<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<Quark3>
    <chapter title="Forward">
        <co authors="Samuel R. Delany &amp; Marilyn Hacker">
            <quote by="Ludwig Wittgenstein, Tractatus Logico-Philosophicus">
                <section number="2.0121">2.0121 ... Just as we are quite unable to imagine
                        <impossible think="imagine">spatial objects outside space or temporal
                        objects outside time</impossible>, so there is no object that we can imagine
                    excluded from the possibility of combining with others. If I can imagine objects
                    combined in states of affairs, I cannot imagine them excluded from the
                    possibility of such combination.</section>
                <section number="2.022">2.022 It is obvious that an imagined world, however
                    different it may be from the real one, must have something—a form—in common with
                    it. —Ludwig Wittgenstein, Tractatus Logico-Philosophicus</section>
            </quote>
            <reflection>
                <section> which is the best explanation why there is "speculative
                    fiction."</section>
                <section>An aesthetic object (a work of art? a story?) has internal tensions (form?)
                    and also produces tensions with its environment. The resultant matrix of forces
                    is called "audience reaction."</section>
                <section>As writers, we can't control the real world. At best, we can observe it
                    actively. We can control the internal tensions of the aesthetic objects of our
                    making. Any of the "commercial writing tricks" to control reader reaction are a
                    waste of time because they are attempts to control the real world, which is
                    impossible, and distract from the time spent controlling internal tensions which
                    —while they do not control audience reaction—are the workable points at which it
                    is moored.</section>
                <section>The attitude of the more commercial science fiction writers in its most
                    articulate expression: "I am not an artist. I am a craftsman. I am concerned
                    with entertainment, not aesthetics. Science fiction is the only area of popular
                    literature whose basic entertainment value is intellectual—technological or
                    sociological—which makes it a socially valuable genre per se. You experimental
                    writers, by your emphasis on aesthetics, have blurred the major valid claim SH
                    has as a socially functional literature."</section>
                <section>But the problems of entertainment are aesthetic problems. If the definition
                    of "entertainment" is allowed to include the emotions, the intellect, and the
                    pure pleasure we take in form, then all aesthetic problems are problems of
                    entertainment. Aesthetic discipline is that which makes most accessible all the
                    substance of a given work. The writer who declines to make use of the full range
                    of aesthetic discipline in deference to entertainment is cheating the reader of
                    the entertainment he claims to be concerned with.</section>
                <section>The argument for the social value of art over propaganda is too tedious and
                    too familiar to reproduce here. A great deal of very good "classic" SF was done
                    in the U.S. during the disasters of the (first) McCarthy period, when it was
                    practically impossible to make a socially pertinent statement in any area other
                    than science fiction.</section>
                <section>People were invariably astounded that so much freedom did exist within the
                    genre. But the official reaction was that SF was lunatic and not to be taken
                    seriously.</section>
                <section>Underneath that rather cavalier insult is a considerable truth: Within the
                    aesthetic structure laid out by "the adventure story" it is impossible to
                    produce a politically dangerous fiction, no matter how revolutionary the
                    proposed world is, no matter what evils the hero is faced with, nor how
                    congruent they are to the present ones. </section>
                <section>The efficacy of "political" fiction, from the point of view of the body
                    politic, is measured precisely in terms of real action it can cause ... and
                    presumably becomes dangerous when somebody notices this action. The adventure,
                    with its building tensions suddenly relieved, its preoccupation with the
                    physical rather than the psychological, its linearity, simply doesn't leave
                    enough residue of discomfort in the mind to precipitate action. This is what
                    dooms a social criticism set in this form to political inconsequence.</section>
                <section> The two fiction works in the U.S. that have been near revolutionary, Uncle
                    Tom's Cabin and Babbitt, are, despite whatever barbarousnesses they contain,
                    social chronicle novels, not adventures.</section>
                <section>One's only objections to science fiction "of value as social criticism" is
                    precisely that it failed to be dangerous, because of an aesthetic choice by the
                    authors deferring to "popular entertainment."</section>
                <section>A willingness to take risks means health and vitality in any artistic
                    field. An unwillingness to take risks means stagnation, death. To view
                    meaningfully the social, psychological, and technological crises present by the
                    particular illumination generated by the forms and textures of speculative
                    fiction, we must encourage as much experimentation as possible, so that this
                    illumination will reach beyond the boundary timid parents have tried to
                    prescribe for their vigorous children.</section>
            </reflection>
        </co>
    </chapter>
    <DogInAFishermansNet>
        <chapter title="DogInAFishermansNet">
            <author by="Samuel R. Delany"><section> After the storm, Panos spread the nets on the
                    concrete, while his younger brother moved the iced crated fish from deck to
                    dock. Spyro cuffed him to let him know he was finished. Panos grunted, the warm
                    long sound a bear makes when satisfied. "Ya!" he called as Spyro started back to
                    the boat. "Take her behind the spit. And rope the nets to the rail this time.
                    I'll mend these dry ones."</section>
                <section>"Ne," Spyro yelled above the clashing hulls and vaulted to the deck.
                    Loosed, the line spun from the piling as the boat rocked backwards. Panos worked
                    his toes on the crumbling jetty edge.</section><section> Beneath the ghost
                    lights that sheeted half the sky, two more boats bucked through the froth that
                    lazed on the water. A wave slapped stone and flung drops higher than his head.
                    Gold fell from cloudings east, and Panos squinted.</section><section> When he
                    walked to the center of the net, his knees jabbed from his pants. There were
                    drops like tears on his face, jewels in his hair and sweater.</section>
                <section>With bowed legs resting on their heels, he sat now and pulled up a ruined
                    section into his lap, hooking the meshes out with his toes to keep it straight.
                    The knife with which he cut the broken threads clean had been whet an hour that
                    morning while he'd waited to go out. With orange thread on a bone shuttle, he
                    retied the running diamonds.</section>
                <section>When the fishing boats slammed in he only looped the knots more quickly,
                    not looking up. Shouting; dogs circling toward the dock; water—the shuttle
                    danced in the webbing. Behind him a truck from the obsidian mines growled. The
                    three o'clock freighter would be late because of the storm. He heard a handful
                    of stones chuckle over the sideboards. Near, a running dog...</section>
                <section>At the tug under the seat of his pants, he looked back over his shoulder.
                    Legs flipped up, a pink mouth choked off a howl, and corks jumped on net
                    wings.</section>
                <section>The dog barked, tried to shake off the strings, fell, kicked. Panos,
                    roaring, whirled to his knees and grabbed. His own feet snagged and he stumbled.
                    Sinkers rasped concrete. The dog bounded, was dragged back. Panos caught one leg
                    and lost balance. When he jerked his hand back from the teeth, his fingers
                    carried harsh threads across his own face. As he tried to roll from the yelping
                    animal, his hand went out, stopped in string, then worse, went through. Threads
                    chattered.</section>
                <section>Men from the boats and the truck ran up. The one with the stick—behind
                    orange strings, Panos saw him hesitate —struck at the dog's head. Netting
                    strained under a cracked boot with toes showing. Netting tore. He tried to push
                    the men away. They were making it worse. Again the stick, but this time it went
                    on to strike the bony point of his shoulder. Fur twisted on his chest, and a
                    hind foot pawed his cheek.</section>
                <section> Someone else was pushing the men aside, and Panos saw Costa, all hair and
                    grooved muscle, drop to his knees and raise a piece of concrete. The
                    road-mender's arm was tarred to the elbow. The rock fell, Panos jerked; and
                    something jabbed his neck </section><section>... The knife! The blade, snagged
                    in the net, had pierced him, hard. Costa had struck the dog again, and the
                    barking stopped. Someone kicked at the limp, sticky thing, but when Panos pulled
                    away, somehow the point slipped in another surprising inch. Panos opened his
                    mouth to scream and his mouth flooded with something salty, salty as the
                    sea.</section>
                <section>Costa, wielding the clotted rock, pushed back the men. They were shouting.
                    "Hey, Paniyotis!"</section><section> From another, "Ya! Move back
                    there!"</section>
                <section>And, "Open the net! Slowly, slowly! Ne! The bitch has torn it
                    enough."</section>
                <section>The last words were stones in a pool of silence.</section>
                <section>Two crossed themselves. Two more the same. Costa backed against the waiter
                    who had come out from Alexeis, jumped, and in confusion flung the rock to the
                    water. Behind them another boat clattered, and from the head of the dock Spyro
                    shouted, "Ya, somebody take this box!"</section><section> No one turned. And
                    lowered the boxes himself, jerking his scarred fingers out in time. At the
                    multiple crash, the top box nearly fell, but he caught it. "What are you staring
                    at there?"</section><section> The men blinked at him. Costa whispered, "Your
                    brother ..."</section><section> Three men clenched their jaws so that their
                    cheeks hollowed suddenly.</section>
                <section>"What about him?" Spyro pushed the box in place. Then he frowned. "The
                    storm blew the mackerel into our net. Has your catch been poor?"</section>
                <section>"Spyro, your brother .." Costa stretched his hand out. Crimson slicked the
                    tar.</section><section> "A dog," the waiter from Alexei's began. "A dog got in
                    the net. We only tried to</section>
                <section>"He was tearing the strings, Spyro."</section>
                <section>"You know the sound of tearing nets is like the Lady's laughter at moondown
                    ..." </section><section>Spyro screamed. Later, he would have said, "I did not
                    see what was tied in the torn cords. I felt it. I felt death in it. It yanked my
                    hands up, snatched my face down and shook me by the tongue. Death stuck two
                    fingers in my eyes. I saw nothing. I felt." They picked him up, first trying to
                    protect themselves, then trying to keep Spyro himself from hurt. Had he reached
                    the body, he would have hugged his own life back into it.</section>
                <section>They took him into the cafe, holding him around the shoulders, holding his
                    arms, his waist, as many as possible touching him with live hands to protect him
                    from the dead thing, Paniyotis.</section><section> Costa told Katina, the girl
                    who served in the cafe, in two grunted sentences what had happened. She smashed
                    her fingertips against her mouth to stop a sound, kneading her lips, and stepped
                    back against the white-washed wall.</section>
                <section>"So easy to die," said an old man, swinging his beads into his fist and
                    silencing them for the first time that day. "So hard to grieve."</section>
                <section>Katina started to run out, but someone grabbed her arm. "Give us coffee.
                    And if you must run, bring a big bowl of soup back from Alexeis. But first give
                    the poor boy brandy."</section>
                <section>With no father or brothers to set dowry, obliged to work, and therefore
                    with no marriage possibilities, her feelings were given little care. She bit her
                    lower lip, went to the liquor shelf and took down the Metaxa. One man called for
                    ouzo, but another punched his arm. "Sheep! You have brandy with the grieving
                    man, or you take only coffee.</section>
                <section>All those crowding Spyro's table urged him to drink from their glasses as
                    well as his own. He took only one sip from Costa's.</section><section> "Panos
                    has had bad luck this whole year. First the falling house wall, then his poor
                    sister who must be married at once ..</section>
                <section>Costa hissed for silence. "Don't weigh yesterday's problems, Grandfather.
                    Today's are heavy enough."</section>
                <section>"And tomorrow's may be heavier," returned the old man, and began to drop
                    his beads again.</section>
                <section>Spyro stood up.</section>
                <section>When he looked around, the four men who had crossed themselves at the dock
                    raised their hands, palms up, to shield his glance. </section><section>"Gotsi!
                    Gotsi!" insisted Costa—Sit down! Sit down!— "Katina, bring him another
                    brandy!"</section><section> But the girl had gone.</section>
                <section>Spyro walked to the door and saw them look at each other to see who would
                    stop him. Before their decision, he was outside.</section>
                <section>Two steps, three steps across the stone apron: nobody called. Unsure why,
                    he walked back to the dock. In the confusion he recalled someone going to see
                    that the body was taken care of but the net still lay over the
                    stain.</section><section> A black-shawled woman whispered something to the men
                    unloading.</section>
                <section>When they saw him look, their hands jumped before their eyes. Then men
                    stooped quickly to their boxes. Spyro turned</section>
                <section>Katina stood at the dock's head. Her oiled braid looped across the shoulder
                    of her green sweater. The glance of a grieving man brings grief, he thought, and
                    waited for her to raise her hand or look away. He saw fear in her face, but she
                    did not try to cover it. There was something else, to which he could not fit a
                    name. Words growled up from his belly, but stumbled once in his mouth so that he
                    could only blurt, hoarsely, "It was my brother!"</section>
                <section>A memory began to beat behind his eyes, hammering out Katina's face. It
                    came by piece and patch. Then, with urgent vividness, it flooded:</section>
                <section>Panos had borrowed a shotgun. They had saved a month for cartridges. He had
                    wrapped rags around his feet, Panos had borrowed rubber boots, and they had gone
                    hunting in the central mountains of the island, taking turns with the gun. That
                    afternoon they brought home six rabbits to Piope.</section>
                <section>She jumped when they came in, and the box of seashells she had been looking
                    through scattered on the floor. Laughing and crying, she said she had been
                    terrified all day that one brother would accidentally shoot the other.</section>
                <section>"Do you worry every time we go out on the boats each morning one of us will
                    drown?" Panos grinned.</section><section> She looked at the shells over the
                    packed dirt, then took the rabbits with an amused glance (hints of something
                    very deep and very frightening as well as frightened always shone in her black,
                    tear-bright eyes), then came back from the stone sink, brushing her light hair
                    from her forehead. There was a scar high on her right temple from the time, as a
                    little girl, some boys threw rocks at her when she tried to play with
                    them.</section><section> Both Spyro's and his brother's hair was
                    black.</section>
                <section>Piope's hair—it looked like sun in a copper cauldron filled with oil—had
                    upset their mother terribly. She had used calimari ink to darken it and made
                    Piope wear a kerchief every time she went outside to keep the sun from
                    lightening it more. Now Piope's emotions fell like half-lights about the house.
                    Things from outside brought her easily to tears or laughter, so most of the time
                    she stayed indoors, at housework, or playing with the shells her brothers
                    brought her.</section><section> The broiled rabbit was tender and full-flavored,
                    crisp with its slight fat, and juicy. Spyro was so after Panos to go again he
                    could hardly keep his feet under him on the sloppy deck. Finally Panos took him
                    up as far as the limestone bluffs where, beside a bush of paddle cactus leaves,
                    they found a waist-high cypress sapling with half-exposed roots clawing the
                    white earth. With twigs pegged to the ground, and fishing line, Panos built a
                    snare.</section>
                <section>They left the sapling bent double in the October wind. In the morning the
                    sapling was straight, and the dangling hare, hind foot snapped and bloody, was
                    half dead from exhaustion.</section>
                <section>After that they had a rabbit nearly every other day. Then Spyro found a
                    second sapling and they sometimes had two at once. That was when the house wall
                    fell.</section><section> They were coming back from the bluff, two bloody-footed
                    hares at Spyro's waist, when confusion met them at the edge of the town. In the
                    mountains they hadn't even felt the tremor, but along the shore it had been more
                    severe, and the radio said that windows had been broken in Athens. But only two
                    kouses had suffered in the island's harbor town. One was a half-completed
                    structure being built by old Austinos.</section>
                <section>The other was theirs. The side wall was rubble. The bamboo roof sagged like
                    cloth, raveled at the edges with dried seaweed and cracked mud. Piope, her face
                    sore from spent hysteria, blinked in the painful sun, as she paused in her hunt
                    among the stone for broken shells. When somebody tried to talk to her, she cried
                    again, shaking her scarfed head, and ran behind the gnarled almond tree if they
                    persisted.</section>
                <section>When Spyro reached the yard through his chattering neighbors, fear filled
                    his mouth like rocks. The shattered familiar, the safety of his birthplace
                    broken, tried to force up questions, but rock sealed his throat. Panos, what
                    must we do? But he was as incapable of speech as Piope.</section>
                <section>Unasked, Panos answered.</section>
                <section>He pulled the rabbits from Spyro's belt, went into the house, and came out
                    with the rafia-covered wine jar that had escaped, under the sink. "Costa," he
                    said, "don't get too drunk this evening." He handed the jar to the tarry
                    workman. "You will have to help us tomorrow."</section><section> A bony
                    seven-year-old, in a pair of men's army pants ripped off above the knees and
                    bound with rusty bailing cable over his hollow belly, stared across his
                    knuckles. "Take these to your aunt." Panos held out the rabbits. "Perhaps they
                    won't fill you for long, but they'll fatten the worms in your gut some." The
                    boy's scaly eyelids widened. Then he snatched the rabbits and fled.</section>
                <section>Spyro got his voice back. "Our house falls in, and you give away everything
                    that remains to us?"</section>
                <section>"A few little presents" Panos said, squeezing the back of Spyro's neck.
                    "Are you hungry for wine and broiled rabbit?"</section><section> Spyro squinted
                    into the house. "This makes me sicker than any storm. I couldn't hold
                    food."</section>
                <section>"Well then?" Panos picked out a shell from under fallen mortar and thumbed
                    the crumbs away. "We only have a little on this island, and still She snatches
                    at it. Though the good Father prays to Kyrios Jesus for us, it may still be as
                    the herders say."</section>
                <section>"You think because Kyrios Jesus was buried in a stone tomb instead of soil,
                    his body cannot make the land prosper?" Panos shrugged. "Even with all the
                    cactus and bramble, there are still oranges, olives, and tomatoes enough. I only
                    mean that when the Lady shows Her caprice to one of us, that man must busy his
                    mind thinking of others, or his own misery will paralyze him. What are you
                    crying about, Piope?" He handed his sister the shell and pulled her to him while
                    she stood holding it. "The widow Mardoupas has gone to pick up olives for oil
                    this morning. It would take more than an earthquake to stop her fingers. That
                    wise woman's stories made you laugh when you were a little girl. Go help her
                    now, and perhaps you will come home in the evening laughing, even to this." He
                    nodded back down the road. "Come," he said to Spyro.</section>
                <section>The donkey trail they walked was walled with granite and red marble.
                    Burros, carrying brush and vegetables between the harbor town of Adamas and the
                    old city, the Plaka, kept the runnel blotched with old or steaming lumps over
                    the yellow carpet. The land, brown two months ago in summer, rose now in green
                    terraces on both sides. They turned for a while up the asphalt road till it left
                    the shadow of the bluffs for the sun and the hot macadam stung through their
                    callouses and forced them to the chalk ditch at the road's edge, where they were
                    dusted white to the knees.</section>
                <section>They crossed a grape arbor where the jointed vines lay like crabs on the
                    cracked ground; then up another walled path that wound higher till the wind at
                    the crest slapped the backs of their necks and brushed their hair forward.
                    Halfway down they met some twenty goats, driven by a herder with a skinny face
                    and most of his nails rotten from injuries scrabbling after his charges. He
                    spoke with the half incomprehensible, sing-song speech of the old mountains. His
                    gray eyes glittered behind pale hair that beat down his forehead in the wind. He
                    knew a lot of stories, some filthy, most funny, as well as all the old tales.
                    Spyro had spent much time wondering, as had most fishermen, at the brown-haired,
                    light-eyed inlanders with their priest-less churches where goats were killed;
                    who came into Adamas or the Plaka to drink only at October's equinox, when the
                    men boasted openly in the cafes of sexual intercourse with other men, women, or
                    their beasts. They kept their boys for work and sent their girls to the Plaka
                    gymnasium, and left the handling of money to the women as well, saying that
                    reading, writing, and numbers were a sort of magic, and magic was Her
                    province.</section><section> Reaching under his chamois vest to scratch, the
                    herder grimaced. "My sister can write the name of every man in the family, as
                    well as put down a story you tell her one day so that she can give you back the
                    same words in a month's time; and she is not yet fifteen."</section><section>
                    Spyro had been to the Plaka gymnasium for a year and had seen a few of the
                    brown-haired mountain girls. "What was your sister's name?"</section>
                <section> Curiosity impelled the question, but the herder jabbed him with a wrinkled
                    fist, and though he joked, his tone held alarm. "If She would not tell Her name
                    to any man, why should I tell the name of a woman of my family to
                    you?"</section><section> The goats clicked out across the red and orange clays
                    that streaked the hillside. The highest peak of the island heaved from beneath
                    the Plaka, topped with an abandoned monastery, like a jawbone in the clear, late
                    light. Left, terraces lowered to the sea.</section><section> When Panos turned
                    onto the stone channel that dropped toward the ruins beside the Old City, the
                    herder laughed. wake go now to where She sleeps. Be quiet, or She may
                    wake."</section><section> Panos only grinned at the little fellow once, but
                    Spyro kept glancing back to where the goatherd bobbed with his flock as he
                    guided it back to town. At last Spyro sat with his brother on the tower
                    foundation, the old Roman ampitheater above and to the left, the water below.
                    The bay arcing away should be a haven for fish, deep and undisturbed by
                    freighters. But no Christian fisherman brought his boat here. Sometimes herders
                    came to drop handlines from the rocks, but those fishermen who chanced the
                    bay—and at the Orthodox Father's urging, each year a few would try—always
                    returned with tales of snagged nets, or groundings where no rocks should be. Far
                    along the coast, at the craggy brim of the island, smoke trickled from the
                    mines.</section><section> Panos hugged in his knees, pulling chalky feet across
                    the stone.</section><section> "Why?" ventured Spyro at last. "Why did we come
                    here?" </section>
                <section>His brother gestured with his chin. "Why do you think?" As the sun at the
                    horizon slit sky from water, pale gold bled on the waves. The evening was
                    bruised with copper sores.</section>
                <section>"It is beautiful."</section>
                <section>"Yes."</section>
                <section>"But still, why did we come?"</section><section> "We have had a misfortune.
                    First we have given a little to our neighbors. Now we must give a little to to
                    the gods."</section>
                <section>"To Kyrios Jesus, you mean?"</section>
                <section>Though Paniyotis' eyes were black, they shone a moment like a herder's. "If
                    it please you."</section>
                <section>"Then why do you come to where She sleeps to pray to Kyrios
                    Jesus..."</section><section> "I said nothing about prayer. Besides, how can She
                    sleep here when the English archaeologists came and dug Her up and took Her away
                    a hundred years ago. She may have slept here once, but now She is in a museum in
                    Paris, in France. Your grandfather worked on the crew that found Her. What did
                    they teach you in that year at the gymnasium, anyway?"</section>
                <section>"They told us about that," Spyro nodded. "But the herders say She was not
                    in the earth at all, but in the sea."</section>
                <section>"You say one thing. I say another. Come." "You say one thing. I say
                    another. Come." He rubbed the back of Spyro's neck. "You must give something
                    too. But it must be of yourself, and quietly."</section><section> Afterwards
                    they walked home by moonlight. Though the November days were warm enough, the
                    nights were cold. When they followed the road into the shadow of the lime
                    bluffs, Spyro could hardly see, and had to blink after his brother, a shadow
                    before him on the night road.</section>
                <section>And blinking brought back Katina's face, still before him on the busy dock,
                    wide-eyed, but steadily watching. "It was my brother," he repeated.</section>
                <section>She whispered something he hardly heard, and seemed near running
                    away.</section><section> "What?"</section><section> "I said," she repeated, " It
                    was my dog?'"</section>
                <section>"Yours..?" The mucilage that held sound to meaning had come unstuck. Spyro
                    struggled to fix it.</section>
                <section>"He came to the cafe once when the boys had thrown cans at him and cut his
                    side, here. I put iodine on the cut so it wouldn't run. Then I fed him and let
                    him sleep in my room. Now they have killed my dog ..." She dropped her eyes. "
                    ... and your brother." The last was softer; he watched the small jumping muscle
                    in her cheek.</section>
                <section>"But he was in the nets," Spyro said, for the first time trying to explain
                    to himself what had been done. "He was tearing them, and there was no time to
                    untangle him slowly. Each time he turned, he wrecked a day's damage. They had to
                    kill him because he would have ruined the strings beyond retying if they tried
                    to take him out slowly. The sound of tearing nets is like the Lady's laughter.
                    It was or hide the in he caught and then there was no..."</section>
                <section>Horror had built in her. "you mean the dog" face she said suddenly,
                    comprehending.</section> "<section>The dog, yes. Of course I mean the
                    dog!"</section>
                <section>"But Paniyotis"</section>
                <section>At the name, rhythmic explosions began in his chest. The greatest part of
                    grief is fear. "My brother ..."</section>
                <section>"It was an accident," repeated Katina, her voice hoarse. "Oh, yes. They saw
                    the nets going, and they ran to help, to save those terrible
                    nets!"</section><section> He could understand her sorrow over the pet, but the
                    hard, flat anger that struggled under the words was disproportionate. "What sort
                    of men are they that they could not even see the trapped man for the dog. Oh,
                    yes, it was an accident they killed him ..</section><section> "You mean my
                    brother!" Now surprise was his.</section><section> "Your brother, yes. Of course
                    I mean your brother!" Her voice, emptied of outrage, became subtle and forlorn.
                    "I do not like this island. Here they do not know which is more important, a
                    fisherman or his nets. Someday," her eyes moved from thing to thing across the
                    dock, "I am going to leave Milos. I will go to Syros, where they have many boats
                    everyday, from Piraeus to Mykonos, and Rhodos. I can go to Idra, or St. Orini,
                    or visit my aunt in Athens anytime I want, instead of waiting for the one boat
                    here from Piraeus every Sunday. I do not like it here." </section><section>He
                    smiled, having heard her say this before, usually in exasperation at some man in
                    the cafe. Her eyes returned to him, but Spyro walked back to his stack of fish
                    boxes. A dozen women had been picking among the fish from the other boats. The
                    smaller fish were piled on newspapers or verdigrised brass trays; the medium
                    ones were in wide enameled baskets, and the larger were laid across iced boxes
                    in alternate directions.</section><section> Spyro started to take the top box
                    down, then paused to look at four girls, near Katina's age, but of good family,
                    strolling with joined arms toward the dock.</section>
                <section>Two old men with string shopping bags nodded and smiled to them, inquired
                    after their fathers, turning to watch them go on. Austinos, the older man, had
                    let it be known that as soon as his six months of mourning were over and the
                    black armband came off, he would take a third wife. Panos had once proposed,
                    against all advice and reason, to Ana, the prettiest and strongest of the four.
                    The existence of unmarried Piope, whose house and dowry had not been settled,
                    aside from his fluctuating income, made it a ludicrous proposition. Her father
                    had instructed Ana to refuse him. Six months would probably see Austinos with
                    her or her sister.</section>
                <section>Spyro slid the box across the deck, and pulled back the lid. Beside the
                    mackerel, there were seven eels, four black ones and three gold-flecked marinas
                    with long mouths. When all the boxes were open, he planted his feet wide apart
                    and called out, "I have fish here, and today free! Here is a gift to anyone who
                    wants it! Here is fish that the sea gave me for nothing but the sweat on my
                    arms. The price to you is the work it takes to carry it home! Fish! Fish! Free
                    fish here!" </section><section>One girl with Ana laughed and began to pull the
                    others toward Spyro's boxes. They were beaten by a little girl who pointed to
                    the largest mackerel and demanded, "That one!" She grabbed it by the tail with
                    her left hand, thought again, and grabbed a second with her right, and ran.
                    Austinos, exhorting people to respect his sixty-seven years (they ignored him),
                    pushed a marina in his string bag. A woman jostled him, and the gold and black
                    length slithered from an opening and was crushed by bare feet and booted. Spyro
                    himself pushed away. Women were running toward the crowd. Children streaked off
                    with fish over their shoulders. And one woman waddled away with six in her
                    apron.</section>
                <section>Something more powerful than sorrow, but propelled by it, erupted from him.
                    The full sound clanged in his throat for seconds before he recognized his own
                    laughter. Katina watched wondrously from the other side of the dock. Slapping
                    his thighs, Spyro turned from the jetty.</section>
                <section>A circle of stone about him. Grass, mud, gravel, and a cus it ste. This
                    shuteed smoth op yourself, Spyro thought, and quietly.</section>
                <section>But all he had were memories of Panos. They clawed, would not loosen, even
                    though he was exhausted with them: Panos yawning at dawn, cursing at noon,
                    laughing in the evening at the cafe. The laughter, still on Spyro's face, only
                    netted the beasts. But oh, they turned and tore and twisted.</section>
                <section>Below lay the harbor of the Old City, abandoned now for less accessible
                    Adamas from which the brothers had fished. Spyro climbed from the foundation and
                    crossed the terrace. Above were the catacombs from the time the island had been
                    under Rome. She had wanted the mines, of course. At the gymnasium he learned
                    that Rome was the capital of Italy. Italian sailors worked on the freighters
                    that carried the obsidian and the clay. The mates and captains let their little
                    fingernails grow long, the same as the bank clerks and the waiter of Alexeis in
                    Adamas, or the Greek sailors from the National Navy who sometimes took their
                    leaves on the island. Spyro knew a war had ended about the time of his birth, in
                    which Greeks fought Italians. His uncle had gone all the way to Albania to
                    fight, and still told stories to anyone who would listen. In class, Spyro had
                    asked if that were the war which had ended the Roman control of the mines and
                    the Old City. Some people laughed. That laughter, which was frequent, was one
                    reason Spyro had left the gymnasium. "Twenty years, two thousand years!" His
                    teacher had exploded. "Does it take such great intellect to distinguish between
                    the two?" With many of the students, both herders and fishermen, this was his
                    most frequent chastisement. When Spyro announced at home he was not going back,
                    Paniyotis had been quietly angry, and Piope had whispered, "I wish I could go to
                    the gymnasium at Plaka." </section><section>"What? Like some herder's girl?"
                    Panos snapped, and Piope, pulling her kerchief up over her strange, lovely hair,
                    moved into the corner. But his brother's and sister's disappointment shadowed
                    the house for days;_Spyro spent most of his free time in the cafe over small
                    cups of coffee, playing at tavli or cards with the older fishermen when no money
                    was involved. After all, he was a boy, and must be allowed to do what he
                    wanted.</section>
                <section>Spyro dropped to the last rock by the water. The small Aegean tide rilled
                    his feet, and to the right a stone inlet roared with froth. No matter which
                    branch of the possible future he looked at, the fruit was ripe loneliness, to
                    feed the beasts:</section><section> Panos flinging an octopodia again and again
                    on the jetty, to tenderize it, till froth covered the stone: Panos after too
                    much ouzo, stealing—well, borrowing, since he returned it the next day—the
                    out-of-tune saturi hanging on the wall at Alexes, sneaking beneath the window of
                    Ana's father the night his proposal had been refused, to set up a tinny racket
                    on the unharmonied strings till the noise ended with her father's curses, and
                    the curses with his own laughter: or later, the same morning, when it turned
                    chilly and Spyro climbed to the roof to take a blanket to his brother who had
                    insisted on sleeping up there the rest of the night, Panos, hunched in the
                    corner, crying.</section>
                <section>Then, again, there was Panos, his hand hard and sweating on Spyro's
                    shoulder, when they danced together in line with the other men at the St.
                    Barbara's day festa. St. Barbara was patron of the miners. The weather had
                    threatened since morning. Below the mine shacks the sea ground the rocks. Piope,
                    even with the house rebuilt, was still un-happy, so they had taken her to the
                    party and, when the dancing began, left her with widow Mardoupas and the other
                    women, and joined the line of men who stamped and ducked with arms around each
                    other's shoulders. Costa pounded his drum with his black fist and those that
                    could stuffed hundred drachma notes in the little hole at the top. Someone from
                    the Plaka had tuned the saturi and hammered out the insistent melodies, while a
                    fiddler, who had come from Sifnos for the day on a fishing boat, razored the
                    winds with his howling box. There were miners, herders, and fishermen, as well
                    as soldiers from the National Army Airport at the far side of the island who
                    were only allowed in town five at a time, and whose presence most people usually
                    ignored.</section>
                <section>The herders were welcomed this time because they brought three roasted
                    goats. The trouble started when one of the soldiers, who was from the Macedonia,
                    took a herder aside and tried to tease him into teaching him one of the goat
                    dances. They danced together, the soldier clumsily, the herder nimbly, miming
                    obscenities at one another. Spyro and Panos watched with the other men, and
                    Spyro laughed till his throat was sore. Then Austinos came over and objected,
                    and some other people who had laughed at first now grew offended and called for
                    an end. The musicians stopped, the soldier apologized and sat down, but the
                    herder kept on. Then his friends came and danced too. The herder women began to
                    sing for the men and stamp their sandals. When anyone tried to stop a man, he
                    would make dirty signs and pull away laughing. Then one old woman, at least
                    thirty, in a skirt made from a silk house coat thrown out by some woman in town,
                    with necklaces of shells, teeth, and polished wood, started to do the forbidden
                    dance that the women do alone in the mountains. Some of the fishermen cried out.
                    Someone called the herders gypsies and said they should go away and leave decent
                    people alone. Three boys were suddenly beside her, their light eyes frightened,
                    but their hands knotted. Two older men stepped beside her as well, one with arms
                    like rocks in a sausage skin. The other could have been the goatherd they'd met
                    before on the road. "How come you have men about you, Lady?" It was Costa who
                    called. Though his tone was contemptuous, he still called her Lady rather than
                    woman. "Who are these standing by you now?"</section>
                <section>"These are my sons" She gestured to the boys. "And these are their
                    fathers." People gasped, but she creased her lips back from yellow teeth.
                    "Though I need not one of them to protect me from any man here." Just then the
                    Orthodox Father, who had been taking a glass of sweet samos in another shack,
                    came up to see what the confusion was, still holding a half-eaten, winy apple.
                    "Come now, come now," he said, striding through the crowd by the door where the
                    dancing had been going since noon. The sun was down and there was only gray
                    light left in the west. "This is a holiday," the Father said. "A Saint's day.
                    This is no time to quarrel." The Father wore his long hair in a little bun at
                    the back, as the herder men did, and most of them respected him. But the woman
                    ...</section>
                <section>The old woman in the bright dress gave a growl of
                    disgust.</section><section> Panos, who was holding Spyro's arm, suddenly
                    squeezed. They had laughed at the dance before, but it was suddenly as if the
                    lewdness had been ripped away revealing-evil or good, Spyro did not know, but it
                    was vast as the secrets behind his sister's unsettling stare.</section><section>
                    "Be friends, ," continued the Father, "this is Saint Barbara's
                    day."</section><section> "You dirty Her with a name that can be said by men!"
                    the woman answered with drawling contempt that turned to rasping laughter. "You
                    try to make Her a saint, a chattel to your weak little god who can die and be
                    reborn only once. It is Her day, the day of the Earth, that potters and farmers
                    and miners have held holy since before your weakling came to die in his turn as
                    gods before him have died, as gods will die after him, while She rules
                    forever."</section>
                <section>"My daughter…."</section>
                <section>The woman stamped her foot, spat, and everyone, including the Father,
                    jumped. Just then the whole sky split, and trundled into the sea. The priest
                    went down on his knees with his hands over his face. Some people screamed, and
                    Spyro's heart pounded so slowly and hard his chest ached, and he felt weak. Rain
                    flushed from the clouds as the last light disappeared. When Spyro wiped water
                    from his face, he saw all the herder women were dancing. Fear and fascination
                    ranged through the miners and fishermen who had run from the other shacks to
                    see. Men hustled their wives, sisters, or daughters away so they would not see,
                    or perhaps learn from the forbidden steps and rhythms, then rushed back across
                    the mud to watch for themselves. People jostled, pushed, and somewhere a fight
                    began. Panos had to shake Spyro's arm three times before he gained his brother's
                    open-mouthed attention. "Piope! Where's Piope!"</section>
                <section>Spyro closed his mouth and shook his head. "I don't ..."</section><section>
                    "For the sake of Kyrios Jesus, find Piope, before ." Thunder deadened his last
                    words, and Panos lurched away.</section><section> Spyro started in the other
                    direction. In a lightning blaze, he recognized his sister. Her scarf had blown
                    off and her hair streamed. He grabbed her hand, but the gray eyes that turned to
                    him were a stranger's. The shell of her ear, the high-boned cheek, the corner of
                    her wet mouth gleamed in yellow light from the shack window. As the rain roared
                    between them, he tried to pull away, but the herder woman grabbed his other hand
                    and leaned close, hissing, or was it singing, in that odd accent between music
                    and laughter, "Come with me, Greek. Lie down on your back in the wet earth, and
                    I will ride you where rider never rode horse</section><section> Spyro ran. Water
                    struck his face, got in his throat, and he began to cough. He tried to get
                    inside a shack, but it was too crowded, and people were yelling about something.
                    For a long time he crouched under the dripping eaves in the back, then sounds
                    coming through the rain frightened him, and finally he reached the head of the
                    path back to Adamas.</section>
                <section>Lightning bleached the rock behind a familiar figure twenty feet ahead,
                    bulling through the rain. "Panos!" Spyro began to run. When he grabbed his
                    brother's shoulders, Panos turned and caught him. Spyro pushed his face against
                    the wet sweater. Then he pulled away.</section><section> His brother's back was
                    caked with dirt, too thick for even this torrent to wash away. Spyro ran his
                    hand up through his brother's hair. The front was slick and clean, but the back
                    was filled with mud. Panos started forward angrily. Spyro followed, wiping water
                    from his eyes with his dirtied hand. "Panos, what—"</section>
                <section>Piope reached home the next morning while rain still fell. She was dirty,
                    exhausted, and immediately caught a fever that lasted nearly a week. Three
                    months later, Paniyotis had to pay Marias, the carpenter who had lost his arm in
                    a freighter winch last year, and so could never be more than an assistant, five
                    thousand drachmas to take Piope for his wife, and Spyro had to work a month on
                    his sister's new house under Marias' crabby and impatient
                    instructions.</section><section> The time just before the wedding was strained,
                    and Piope cried most of it. Once she broke all her shells and ran into the
                    mountains where something unpleasant must have happened; when she came back
                    three days later, she had strange scratches on her face that couldn't have been
                    from brambles, for they were in ordered, parallel strokes. She refused to tell
                    what had happened. But during the whole time, where many a father or brother
                    would have turned her out, Panos never said a word of
                    reproach.</section><section> Water lapped from the old bay of Milos, pulling a
                    single file of sand across the rock by Spyro's foot and into the sea. Spyro
                    looked out where She slept. Fear and sorrow tightened his throat. And the fear
                    had to loosen if the sorrow were to leave him.</section>
                <section>Suddenly he pulled his sweater over his head and jerked his wrists from the
                    sleeves. He flung his pants back on top of it. Then he crouched, drew in his
                    breath, and leapt. Water struck cold into the crevices of his body. The winter
                    Aegean warmed to him quickly though. Summer lingered under the sea well into
                    December. Pressure built on his eyes and ears, and he refused to come up, even
                    when over a minute had passed and his chest hurt. He arced before blurred and
                    blued rock. Then something above dove to the water, plummeting in silver toward
                    him. At the same moment, directly before him, he saw the stone thing. Twice
                    broken, it jutted from the rock slope, arms twined with carved snakes and
                    shingled weed. Weed bearded Her gaping face, clotted Her eyes. Spots on Her
                    chipped shoulders glittered gray black. He was very near, perhaps ten feet. As
                    he turned, She waved a long net toward him. As it settled about him, he thought,
                    She isn't asleep! She isn't asleep at all! He clawed still deeper in the cool
                    tow.</section><section> The form above him—a live woman, he realized suddenly
                    reached him at last, seized his hand through the strings. And strings
                    tore.</section>
                <section>As they rolled upward, Spyro looked back to see other webs sailing gently
                    from the stone arms. All the lost nets, snagged yearly from fishing boats that
                    dared Her waters, swirled around the huge, pointed, black breasts.</section>
                <section>The woman beside him tugged his arm, and air began to seep from Spyro's
                    nose, the bubbles tickling his eyelids. He kicked hard, and dragged her half way
                    up before he lost her. When he broke surface, he was blind with pulsing blood,
                    and he thought for a moment he was going to vomit.</section><section> He heard
                    her splash beside him, and took long strokes forward till hands scraped
                    painfully on rock. Water streamed his face and it was hard to hold his head up.
                    She probably one of the strong herder women had been under perhaps half as long
                    as he had. He heard her wet hands slap the rock, a splash, then a slap again as
                    she pushed herself back from the lip. He shook hair and water from his eyes, and
                    looked up.</section>
                <section>Katina, naked and wide-eyed, erouched on the rock, her black braid trailing
                    between her breasts, the ends making little circles against her skin. Her
                    breasts were goose-fleshed around the brown, shriveled nipples. As she gulped
                    her breaths, her stomach, behind the wet braid, took a single crease, smoothed,
                    creased.</section>
                <section>"Why ...?" Below the water he felt warmth coiling through the place where
                    fear had been. Katina, as though she were reaching for something she did not
                    know were hot or cold, took his wrist. "You better come out."</section><section>
                    He nodded, his mouth open—and swallowed brine as a wave washed him. Coughing
                    again, he pushed up on sore hands, then rolled against her. His wet shoulder
                    struck cool against her thigh, then warmth broke through.</section><section>
                    "Why." he asked again, "why are you here?"</section>
                <section>He thought she was going to brush his cheek. But she said, "I come here
                    too, sometimes—when I'm sad. I swim here, because it's alone, and nobody else
                    does, and—I followed you."</section><section> "Why did you follow me—I mean,
                    down there?"</section>
                <section>"When you jumped, I thought you didn't want to come up."</section>
                <section>"I didn't want...?" Though sorrow was still real when he had faced Her
                    beneath the water, the fear had gone. And without it, the laughter came up, this
                    time free and freeing. He lay on his back, rocking his head and laughing, his
                    thick hair sloshing against her calf. Then he took her shoulder and pushed
                    himself to his elbow. Water coursed the runnel of his spine. "Not me! No! When I
                    go down, I come up!" She looked at his horny yellow hand on her
                    shoulder.</section>
                <section>"Men have felt that way before about brothers. Why else should you come
                    here to where She ..." She inclined her head toward the water.</section>
                <section>Spyro dropped his hand to her knee; it fell palm up, the fingers defining a
                    cup. "Tell me, Katina," he whispered, "if She sleeps here, what was it the
                    archaeologists carried away from the slopes that is now in the Paris
                    museum?"</section><section> Katina shrugged. "Just another statue, the same sort
                    as the Turks carried away from here by the dozen. It must have been one the
                    Turks simply overlooked."</section>
                <section>"The herders tell the story, ne?"</section>
                <section>She shrugged. "But the archaeologists should have listened to the herders'
                    tale more closely. The herders say She stood on the top of the tower guarding
                    the old city that was sacred to Her, until the tower fell in an earthquake. We
                    exported obsidian to Egypt even before Minos slung his net over the seas. But
                    that statue they found was of white marble, from Paros, while we have only poor
                    red marble here; and the herders say she was chipped from black glass." She
                    twisted her head to look again.</section>
                <section>"You come to swim here?" He rose to his knees as she turned back. "And you
                    are not afraid of Her?" He stood up. She looked up at him, then suddenly pushed
                    herself back against the rock, pulling in her shoulders. Her lips gemmed with
                    sea water, parted. "But you are afraid of me?"</section><section> She shook her
                    head quickly, but her eyes began to dart around and about his body. What light
                    came past his left hip banded the right side of her face and body with gold.
                    Nakedness, a corollary of circumstance a moment past, was suddenly something
                    powerful about himself, glorious about her. He stooped, bending above her till
                    one knee rubbed against her wet arm, and her staring face darkened with the
                    shadow of his. He took her neck in both hands, as she bent back her head, the
                    muscles stretching under his palms, and touched her ear with lips and teeth at
                    once.</section>
                <section>A goat's bleating above became laughter. Twigs and gravel burned his back,
                    and Spyro leaped away, nearly slipping.</section><section> The goatherds, two
                    boys and a girl, were scrambling up the foundation, looking back, poking each
                    other, and giggling. Glory and power became tingling heat.</section><section>
                    Katina was nervously slipping up her skirt when he looked back. Spyro stood a
                    moment, then, confused, reached for his sweater and butted through the wool for
                    the neck. The knit scratched the skin under his arms.</section>
                <section>At the foundations, Katina hesitated before accepting his hand. He had
                    hesitated before extending it. When she took it, he pulled her up over the rock,
                    and she looked at him very straight all the time. "I don't like this place, this
                    little Island," she began again. "It is somehow like we are all caught in-like
                    Panayotis. Then one dives below and discovers even She is bound in the nets of
                    men." She shook her head. "I do not like this place."</section>
                <section>"I am going to leave Milos," Spyro said.</section><section> They were both
                    surprised. He spoke the thought as he'd formed it, and its articulation was
                    strange and amazing.</section><section> "You are?"</section>
                <section>"Ne. I have nothing here. My sister is married. My brother—is
                    dead."</section>
                <section>"Where are you going?"</section><section> "Piraeus, I think. Yes, to the
                    mainland at Piraeus. I will work on the freighters there."</section><section>
                    "You—really will go?"</section><section> He nodded. "Ne."</section>
                <section>"And it will not be hard for you, just to leave?"</section>
                <section>"Old, water-logged nets tear easily."</section>
                <section>"I am afraid to go," Katina said.</section><section> "I am too," Spyro
                    admitted. "But I'm going." They reached the donkey trail.</section>
                <section>The evening star led the crescent moon from the sea. The sky was purple
                    behind the lime bluffs. They had only been walking a minute when Katina said,
                    "I'm going too."</section>
                <section>Spyro smiled at her, then looked at his feet.</section><section> "I am
                    going to Syros," she went on. "Though I may come to see you in Piraeus. Boats
                    leave from Syros every day, not just once a week. From Syros I can go anywhere.
                    Anywhere!" Suddenly she ran a few steps forward and laughed. From the high bluff
                    laughter returned, as though another woman laughed above them.</section>
                <section>Spyro took her arm and they walked together.</section>
                <section>"I am going," she repeated.</section><section> "I think you are," Spyro
                    said. Then, a few minutes later, when they reached the asphalt road, Spyro said,
                    "I am more important than the nets I cast."</section>
                <section>"Yes." She frowned toward the shadows from the bluff.</section>
                <section>"I think you are."</section></author>
        </chapter>
    </DogInAFishermansNet>
</Quark3>
