<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<?xml-model href="../schema/speculativeFiction.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<xml>
    <header>
        <issue>Quark 3</issue>
        <date when="1971-05">May 1971</date>
    </header>
   
    
    <title>Forward</title>
    
    <epigraph>
        <p><num>2.0121</num> ... Just as we are quite unable to imagine
            spatial objects outside space or temporal
                objects outside time, so there is no object that we can imagine
            excluded from the possibility of combining with others. If I can imagine objects
            combined in states of affairs, I cannot imagine them excluded from the
            possibility of such combination.</p>
        <p><num>2.022</num> It is obvious that an imagined world, however
            different it may be from the real one, must have something—a form—in common with
            it. </p>
        <cit><persName>Ludwig Wittgenstein</persName>, <title>Tractatus Logico-Philosophicus</title></cit>
        
    </epigraph>
      
         
         
                <p> which is the best explanation why there is "speculative
                    fiction."</p>
                <p>An aesthetic object (a work of art? a story?) has internal tensions (form?)
                    and also produces tensions with its environment. The resultant matrix of forces
                    is called "audience reaction."</p>
                <p>As writers, we can't control the real world. At best, we can observe it
                    actively. We can control the internal tensions of the aesthetic objects of our
                    making. Any of the "commercial writing tricks" to control reader reaction are a
                    waste of time because they are attempts to control the real world, which is
                    impossible, and distract from the time spent controlling internal tensions which
                    —while they do not control audience reaction—are the workable points at which it
                    is moored.</p>
                <p>The attitude of the more commercial science fiction writers in its most
                    articulate expression: "I am not an artist. I am a craftsman. I am concerned
                    with entertainment, not aesthetics. Science fiction is the only area of popular
                    literature whose basic entertainment value is intellectual—technological or
                    sociological—which makes it a socially valuable genre per se. You experimental
                    writers, by your emphasis on aesthetics, have blurred the major valid claim SH
                    has as a socially functional literature."</p>
                <p>But the problems of entertainment are aesthetic problems. If the definition
                    of "entertainment" is allowed to include the emotions, the intellect, and the
                    pure pleasure we take in form, then all aesthetic problems are problems of
                    entertainment. Aesthetic discipline is that which makes most accessible all the
                    substance of a given work. The writer who declines to make use of the full range
                    of aesthetic discipline in deference to entertainment is cheating the reader of
                    the entertainment he claims to be concerned with.</p>
                <p>The argument for the social value of art over propaganda is too tedious and
                    too familiar to reproduce here. A great deal of very good "classic" SF was done
                    in the U.S. during the disasters of the (first) McCarthy period, when it was
                    practically impossible to make a socially pertinent statement in any area other
                    than science fiction.</p>
                <p>People were invariably astounded that so much freedom did exist within the
                    genre. But the official reaction was that SF was lunatic and not to be taken
                    seriously.</p>
                <p>Underneath that rather cavalier insult is a considerable truth: Within the
                    aesthetic structure laid out by "the adventure story" it is impossible to
                    produce a politically dangerous fiction, no matter how revolutionary the
                    proposed world is, no matter what evils the hero is faced with, nor how
                    congruent they are to the present ones. </p>
                <p>The efficacy of "political" fiction, from the point of view of the body
                    politic, is measured precisely in terms of real action it can cause ... and
                    presumably becomes dangerous when somebody notices this action. The adventure,
                    with its building tensions suddenly relieved, its preoccupation with the
                    physical rather than the psychological, its linearity, simply doesn't leave
                    enough residue of discomfort in the mind to precipitate action. This is what
                    dooms a social criticism set in this form to political inconsequence.</p>
                <p> The two fiction works in the U.S. that have been near revolutionary, Uncle
                    Tom's Cabin and Babbitt, are, despite whatever barbarousnesses they contain,
                    social chronicle novels, not adventures.</p>
                <p>One's only objections to science fiction "of value as social criticism" is
                    precisely that it failed to be dangerous, because of an aesthetic choice by the
                    authors deferring to "popular entertainment."</p>
                <p>A willingness to take risks means health and vitality in any artistic
                    field. An unwillingness to take risks means stagnation, death. To view
                    meaningfully the social, psychological, and technological crises present by the
                    particular illumination generated by the forms and textures of speculative
                    fiction, we must encourage as much experimentation as possible, so that this
                    illumination will reach beyond the boundary timid parents have tried to
                    prescribe for their vigorous children.</p>
      
        <signature>Samuel R. Delany &amp; Marilyn Hacker</signature>
   
</xml>
